Radical openness is still a distant future
مازالت الرؤية الثورية حلما بعيدا
in the field of school education.
فيما يخص التعليم المدرسي.
We have such a hard time figuring out
مازلنا نعاني من عدم إدراكنا
that learning is not a place but an activity.
بأن التعليم ليس مكانا بل نشاط.
But I want to tell you the story of PISA,
أود أولا إخباركم بقصةالبرنامج الدولي لتقييم الطلبة "پيسا"
OECD's test to measure the knowledge and skills
وهو اختبارلمنظمة التعاون والتنمية الاقتصادية
of 15-year-olds around the world,
لتقييم معارف ومهاراتأطفال أعمارهم 15 سنة حول العالم،
and it's really a story of how international comparisons
وهي بالفعل قصة عن كيف أن المقارنات بين الدول
have globalized the field of education that we usually treat
عولمة مجال التعليم الذي مازلنا نحن نتعامل معه
as an affair of domestic policy.
على أنه قضية سياسية داخلية.
Look at how the world looked in the 1960s,
انظروا كيف كان شكل العالم بالستينات
in terms of the proportion of people
من حيث نسبة السكان
who had completed high school.
الذين أكملوا المرحلة الثانوية.
You can see the United States ahead of everyone else,
يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا أن الولايات المتحدة في الطليعة،
and much of the economic success of the United States
ونسبة كبيرة من نجاحها الاقتصادي
draws on its long-standing advantage
يعود لميزة أنها أول من تحرك
as the first mover in education.
في سبيل التعليم منذ وقت طويل.
But in the 1970s, some countries caught up.
لكن في السبعينات،تمكنت بعض البلدان من تدارك الأمر.
In the 1980s, the global expansion
في الثمانينات، استمر الانتشار العالمي
of the talent pool continued.
للمواهب حول العالم.
And the world didn't stop in the 1990s.
ولم يتوقف العالم في التسعينات.
So in the '60s, the U.S. was first.
في الستينات كانت الولايات المتحدةفي المرتبة الأولى.
In the '90s, it was 13th,
وفي التسعينات بالمرتبة 13
and not because standards had fallen,
ليس لأن معاييرها قد تدهورت
but because they had risen so much faster elsewhere.
بل لأن تلك المعايير تطورت بسرعة مذهلةفي باقي العالم.
Korea shows you what's possible in education.
وكوريا تقدم لكم دليلاعما يمكن القيام به في التعليم.
Two generations ago, Korea had the standard of living
قبل جيلين كان مستوى المعيشة في كوريا
of Afghanistan today,
كمستوى المعيشة في أفغانستان اليوم،
and was one of the lowest education performers.
كان نظامها التعليمي من بينالأنظمة الأقل كفاءة.
Today, every young Korean finishes high school.
واليوم،يكمل كل طفل كوري تعليمه الثانوي.
So this tells us that, in a global economy,
وهذا يدل على أن المؤشر الحقيقي للنجاح،
it is no longer national improvement that's the benchmark for success,
في عصر الاقتصاد العالمي،ليس هو مدى الازدهار الوطني،
but the best performing education systems internationally.
بل مدى كفاءة الأنظمة التعليميةعلى مستوى العالم.
The trouble is that
المشكل هو في
measuring how much time people spend in school
تقدير الوقت الذي يقضيه الناس بالمدرسة
or what degree they have got is not always
أو بأن الشهادة التي تحصلوا عليهاقد لا تكون دائما
a good way of seeing what they can actually do.
أفضل طريقة للتعرف على قدراتهم الحقيقية..
Look at the toxic mix of unemployed graduates on our streets,
انظروا لذلك الخليط السام منالعاطلين ذوي الشهادات بشوارعنا،
while employers say they cannot find the people
بينما المشغلين يقولونأنهم لا يستطعون إيجاد أشخاص
with the skills they need.
يملكون المواهب التي يحتاجون إليها.
And that tells you that better degrees don't automatically translate
وهذا يخبركم بأن أفضل الشهاداتلا تعني دائما
into better skills and better jobs and better lives.
أفضل المهاراتومناصب الشغل ومستويات العيش.
So with PISA, we try to change this
لدى فإننا نحاول تغيير ذلكمن خلال برنامج بيسا
by measuring the knowledge and skills
وذلك بتقييمنا مباشرة المعرفة والمهارات
of people directly.
الموجودة لدى الأشخاص.
And we took a very special angle to this.
ونتبع في ذلك منهجية خاصة.
We were less interested in whether students can simply
لم نكن مهتمين بمدى قدرة الطلاب
reproduce what they have learned in school,
على تطبيق ما تعلموه بالمدرسة
but we wanted to test whether they can extrapolate
بل كنا مهتمين باختبار ما الذي يمكنهم استنتاجه
from what they know
مما يعرفونه
and apply their knowledge in novel situations.
وتطبيق معرفتهم بطرق جديدة.
Now, some people have criticized us for this.
بعض الناس انتقدونا من أجل ذلك.
They say, you know, such a way of measuring outcomes
أخبرونا بأن طريقة كهذه لتقييم النتائج
is terribly unfair to people, because we test students
كانت جد جائرة في حق أولئك الأشخاصلأننا نختبر الطلاب
with problems they haven't seen before.
بمسائل لم يروها من قبل.
But if you take that logic, you know,
لكن إن أخذتم ذلك بهذا المنطق
you should consider life unfair, because
فمن المؤكد أنكم ستجدون أنالحياة نفسها غير عادلة،
the test of truth in life is not whether we can remember
فاختبار الحقيقة في الحياة لا يدورحول ما إن كنا قادرين
what we learned in school,
على تذكر ما تعلمناه بالمدرسة،
but whether we are prepared for change,
بل إن كنا مستعدين للتغيير
whether we are prepared for jobs that haven't been created,
سواء أكنا مستعدين لمنصب الشغل الذيلم نخلقه بعد
to use technologies that haven't been invented,
ولاستخدام التقنيات التي لم نخترعها بعد
to solve problems we just can't anticipate today.
ولحل المشاكل التي لا يمكننا توقعها الآن.
And once hotly contested,
وبعد أن انتِقَدِنَا بشدة،
our way of measuring outcomes has actually quickly become the standard.
أصبحت منهجيتنا في تقييم النتائج اليوموبلمح البصر هي المعيار.
In our latest assessment in 2009,
خلال أخر تقييم لنا سنة 2009،
we measured 74 school systems
قيمنا 74 نظام مدرسي
that together cover 87 percent of the economy.
تمثل مَعاً 87 بالمائة من الاقتصاد.
This chart shows you the performance of countries.
ويُظْهِرُ لكم هذا الرسم البيانيمدى كفاءة الدول.
In red, sort of below OECD average.
بالأحمر، دول تحت معدلمنظمة التعاون والتنمية الاقتصادية.
Yellow is so-so, and in green are the countries doing really well.
بالأصفر المتوسطينوبالأخضر الدول التي قامة بعمل جيد.
You can see Shanghai, Korea, Singapore in Asia;
ويمكنكم مشاهدت أنهاشنغاي وكوريا وسنغافورة بآسيا؛
Finland in Europe;
فنلندا بأوروبا؛
Canada in North America doing really well.
كندا بأمريكا الشمالية يقومون بعمل جيد.
You can also see that there is a gap of almost
يمكنم أيضا أن تلاحظوا أنهناك فارقا يزيد عن
three and a half school years between
ثلاث سنوات دراسية ونصف بين
15-year-olds in Shanghai and 15-year-olds in Chile,
أطفال شنغهاي وأطفال الصينالبالغ عمرهم 15 سنة
and the gap grows to seven school years
ويزيد الفارق إلى سبع سنوات دراسية
when you include the countries with really poor performance.
عند إضافة الدول ذات الأداء الضعيف جدا.
There's a world of difference in the way in which
هناك فارق كبير في الطريقة التي
young people are prepared for today's economy.
يتم إعداد الأطفال لاقتصادنا اليوم.
But I want to introduce a second important dimension
لكني أود أن أقدم لكم البُعْد الثاني المهم
into this picture.
والموجود بتلك الصورة.
Educators like to talk about equity.
المدرسين يحبون الحديث عن الإنصاف.
With PISA, we wanted to measure how they actually deliver equity,
حاولنا من خلال برنامج بيسا تقييمكيف يوفرون الإنصاف،
in terms of ensuring that people
من خلال التأكد من حصول أولائك الناس
from different social backgrounds have equal chances.
ذوي الخلفيات الاجتماعية المختلفةعلى فرص متساوية.
And we see that in some countries, the impact
ونلاحظ بأنه في بعض البلدان، تأثير
of social background on learning outcomes
الخلقية الاجتماعية على النتائج الدراسية
is very, very strong.
جد، جد قوي.
Opportunities are unequally distributed.
الفرص موزعة بشكل غير عادل.
A lot of potential of young children is wasted.
يهدر قدر كبير من إمكانيات الأطفال.
We see in other countries that it matters much less
بينما نلاحظ ببلدان أخرى أنه لا أهمية
into which social context you're born.
للمحيط الاجتماعي الذي ولدت فيه.
We all want to be there, in the upper right quadrant,
جميعنا نرغب بأن نكون بالربع العلوي الأيمن،
where performance is strong and learning opportunities are equally distributed.
حيث الكفاءة قوية وفرص التعليم موزعة بالعدل.
Nobody, and no country, can afford to be there,
لا أحد ولا بلد يرغب بأن يكون حيث
where performance is poor
الكفاءة ضعيفة
and there are large social disparities.
والفوارق الاجتماعية كبيرة.
And then we can debate, you know, is it better
ويمكننا أن نتناقش حول هل من الأفضل
to be there, where performance is strong
أن نكون هناك حيث الكفاءة أقوى
at the price of large disparities?
على حساب الفوارق الاجتماعية الكبيرة؟
Or do we want to focus on equity and accept mediocrity?
أو هل علينا أن نركز على الإنصاف ونقبل بالرداءة؟
But actually, if you look at how countries come out on this picture,
لكن في الحقيقة، إن نظرتم لوضعية الدولفي هذه الصورة،
you see there are a lot of countries that actually
ستلاحظون أن هناك الكثير من الدول التي تجمع
are combining excellence with equity.
بالفعل بين التفوق والإنصاف.
In fact, one of the most important lessons from this comparison
في الواقع، واحد من أهم الدروس المستخلصةمن هذه المقارنة
is that you don't have to compromise equity
أنه ليس عليكم التضحية بالإنصاف
to achieve excellence.
من أجل بلوغ التفوق.
These countries have moved on from providing excellence
لقد تجاوزت تلك الدول مرحلة توفير الإنصاف
for just some to providing excellence for all,
للبعض فقطإلى مرحلة توفير التفوق للجميع.
a very important lesson.
وهو درس في غاية الأهمية.
And that also challenges the paradigms of many school systems
وهو أيضا تحدي للعديدمن نماذج الأنظمة المدرسية
that believe they are mainly there to sort people.
التي تعتقد بأنها وُجِدَت من أجلنوعية محددة من الناس.
And ever since those results came out, policymakers,
ومنذ الإعلان عن تلك النتائج، حاول
educators, researchers from around the world
صناع القرار والمدرسين والباحثين
have tried to figure out
من جميع أنحاء العالم معرفة
what's behind the success of those systems.
ما السر وراء نجاح تلك الأنظمة.
But let's step back for a moment
لكن دعونا نلقي نظرة شاملة
and focus on the countries that actually started PISA,
ولنركز على البلدان التي بدأت بالفعلبتطبيق برنامج بيسا
and I'm giving them a colored bubble now.
وسنمثلها بدوائر ملونة.
And I'm making the size of the bubble
وسأجعل حجم الدائرة
proportional
يتناسب مع
to the amount of money that countries spent on students.
حجم الأموال التي تصرفهاهذه الدول على طلابها.
If money would tell you everything
لو كان المال هو المؤشر القادر على
about the quality of learning outcomes,
إعطائكم فكرة عن مدى جودة نتائج التعليم،
you would find all the large bubbles at the top, no?
فستجدون أن كل الدوائر الكبيرة في القمة،أليس كذلك؟
But that's not what you see.
لكن ليس هذا ما تشاهدونه هنا.
Spending per student only explains about,
فنسبة الإنفاق على كل طالب لا تفسر سوى
well, less than 20 percent
أقل من 20 بالمائة
of the performance variation among countries,
من تفاوت الكفاءة الموجودة بين البلدان.
and Luxembourg, for example, the most expensive system,
فلوكسمبورغ على سبيل المثال،تملك النظام الأكثر تكلفة
doesn't do particularly well.
ومع هذا لا تقوم بعمل جيد.
What you see is that two countries with similar spending
وما تشاهدونه هناهما دولتين تنفقان بنفس الحجم
achieve very different results.
وتحققان نتائج جد مختلفة
You also see -- and I think that's one of the most encouraging findings --
وتشاهدون أيضا-- وفي رأيي هي واحدة من أكثر النتائج تشجيعا --
that we no longer live in a world that is neatly divided
بأننا لم نعد نعيش اليوم بعالم يفرق بشكل دقيق
between rich and well-educated countries,
بين دول غنية ذات تعليم جيد
and poor and badly-educated ones,
وأخرى فقيرة ذات تعليم رديء
a very, very important lesson.
وهذا درس في غاية الأهمية.
Let's look at this in greater detail.
دعونا ندقق النظر في هذا الأمر.
The red dot shows you
النقطة الحمراء توضح لكم
spending per student relative to a country's wealth.
بأن حجم الصرف المخصص لكل طالبيرتبط بثروات البلاد.
One way you can spend money is by paying teachers well,
إحدى الطرق هيبأن تصرف للمدرسين أجور جيدة
and you can see Korea investing a lot
ويمكنكم أن تلاحظو بأن كورياتستثمر بشكل كبير
in attracting the best people into the teaching profession.
في جذب أفضل الأشخاص لمهنة التعليم.
And Korea also invests into long school days,
كما أنها تستثمرفي أيام ذات ساعات دراسية أطول
which drives up costs further.
مما يرفع أكثر فأكثرمن حجم التكلفة.
Last but not least, Koreans want their teachers
أخيرا وليس آخرا،لا يرغب الكوريون في مدرسين
not only to teach but also to develop.
للتدريس فقط بل للتطوير أيضا.
They invest in professional development and collaboration
إنهم يستثمرون بالتطوير المهني والتعاون
and many other things.
وفي أشياء أخرى عديدة.
All that costs money.
وكل ذلك مكلف ماليا.
How can Korea afford all of this?
كيف يمكن لكوريا تحمل كل تلك المصاريف؟
The answer is, students in Korea learn in large classes.
والجواب،الطلاب بكوريا يدرسون في أقسام كبيرة.
This is the blue bar which is driving costs down.
هذا هو الشريط الأزرق الذييخفض من تلك التكاليف.
You go to the next country on the list, Luxembourg,
بانتقالكم للدولة التالية في القائمة،لوكسمبورغ،
and you can see the red dot is exactly where it is for Korea,
يمكنكم ملاحظة أن نقطتها الحمراء تقعبنفس مكان النقطة الحمراء لكوريا،
so Luxembourg spends the same per student as Korea does.
إذا لوكسمبورغ وكوريا تنفقانبنفس القدر للطالب الواحد.
But, you know, parents and teachers and policymakers
لكن الأباء والمدرسين وصناع القرار
in Luxembourg all like small classes.
بلوكسمبورغ يفضلون الأقسام الصغيرة.
You know, it's very pleasant to walk into a small class.
فكما تعلمون فمن المريح السير بأقسام صغيرة.
So they have invested all their money into there,
لدى استثمروا كل أموالهم في ذلك
and the blue bar, class size, is driving costs up.
والشريط الأزرقالخاص بحجم الأقسام يزيد من التكلفة.
But even Luxembourg can spend its money only once,
لكن حتى لوكسمبورغلا يمكنها الإنفاق على أكثر من شيء واحد،
and the price for this is that
والمقابل لذلك هو أن
teachers are not paid particularly well.
أجور المدرسين لديها ليست بالجيدة.
Students don't have long hours of learning.
لا يقضي الطلاب ساعات طويلة بالدراسة.
And basically, teachers have little time to do anything else than teaching.
بينما ليس لدى المدرسينوقت كاف للقيام بأشياء أخرى غير التدريس.
So you can see two countries spent their money very differently,
يمكنكم ملاحظة أنبلدين ينفقان أموالهما بشكل جد مختلف،
and actually how they spent their money
وأن كيفية إنفاق أموالهما هي في الواقع
matters a lot more than how much they invest in education.
أكثر أهميةمن المقدار المالي المستثمر في التعليم.
Let's go back to the year 2000.
فلنعد للعام 2000.
Remember, that was the year before the iPod was invented.
تذكروا،كان ذلك قبل سنة من اختراع أجهزة الأي پود.
This is how the world looked then
هذا ما بدت عليه الكفاءات بالعالم بعدها
in terms of PISA performance.
من منظور برنامج پيسا.
The first thing you can see is that the bubbles were a lot smaller, no?
أول ما يمكن ملاحظته هوتلك الدوائر الصغيرة جدا، أليس كذلك؟
We spent a lot less on education,
كان إنفاقنا جد ضعيف على التعليم،
about 35 percent less on education.
حوالي 35 بالمائة أقل على التعليم.
So you ask yourself, if education has become so much more expensive,
هل تتساءلون إن أصبح التعليم جد مكلف،
has it become so much better?
أو أصبح أفضل؟
And the bitter truth really is that, you know,
والحقيقة المُرَّة بالفعل هي أن
not in many countries.
الأمر ليس كذلك بالعديد من البلدان.
But there are some countries which have seen
لكن هناك بعض الدول التي عرفت
impressive improvements.
تطورات مذهلت.
Germany, my own country, in the year 2000,
ألمانيا سنة 2000، البلد الذي أنتمي إليه،
featured in the lower quadrant,
كانت تقبع بالربع السفلي من الرسم البياني،
below average performance, large social disparities.
تحت متوسط الكفاءات وبفوارق اجتماعية كبيرة.
And remember, Germany, we used to be one of those countries
وتذكروا،أنه كان بإمكان ألمانيا أن تكون من بين تلك البلدان
that comes out very well when you just count people who have degrees.
ذات المراكز الجيدة لو أحصت فقط ذوي الشهادات.
Very disappointing results.
نتائج جد مخيبة للآمال.
People were stunned by the results.
الناس فوجئوا من تلك النتائج.
And for the very first time, the public debate in Germany
وللمرة الأولى، كان التعليم هو المسيطر
was dominated for months by education,
على النقاشات العامة بألمانيا،
not tax, not other kinds of issues, but education
لا ضرائب أو قضايا أخرى، لكن كان
was the center of the public debate.
التعليم هو مركز النقاش العام.
And then policymakers began to respond to this.
ومن ثم بدأ صناع القرار بالإجابة عن ذلك.
The federal government dramatically raised its investment in education.
رفعت الحكومة الاتحادية استثمارهابشكل مدهش في مجال التعليم.
A lot was done to increase the life chances of students
تم القيام بالكثير من أجلتحسين الفرص المعيشية للطلاب
with an immigrant background or from social disadvantage.
المنحدرين من أصول مهاجرةأو من طبقة اجتماعية مهمشة.
And what's really interesting is that this wasn't just about
والمثير في الحقيقة أن الأمر لم يتعلق فقط
optimizing existing policies,
بإصلاح السياسات الموجودة،
but data transformed some of the beliefs and paradigms
بل قامت المعطيات بتغيير بعضالمعتقدات والنماذج
underlying German education.
التي شكلتأساس النظام التعليمي بألمانيا.
For example, traditionally, the education of the very young children
على سبيل المثال،كان تعليم الأطفال في الماضي يعتبر
was seen as the business of families, and you would have cases
واجبا أسريا،وقد تكونوا على علم بحالات
where women were seen as neglecting their family responsibilities
اتهمت فيها بعض النساء بالتقصيرفي واجباتهن الأسرية
when they sent their children to kindergarten.
عند إرسالهن لأطفالهن لروضة الأطفال.
PISA has transformed that debate,
قام برنامج پيسا بتغيير هذا النقاش
and pushed early childhood education right at the center
ووضعت تعليم الأطفال الصغارفي مركز أولويات
of public policy in Germany.
السياسة العامة بألمانيا.
Or traditionally, the German education divides children
تقليديا،كان النظام التعليمي بألمانيا يفرق بين الأطفال
at the age of 10, very young children,
منذ سن 10، وهو سن جد مبكرة،
between those deemed to pursue careers of knowledge workers
بين أولئك الذين سيوجهون إلى مهن عمال المعرفة
and those who would end up working for the knowledge workers,
وأولئك الذين سينتهي بهم المطافللعمل عند عمال المعرفة،
and that mainly along socioeconomic lines,
وكل هذاحسب التوجهات السوسيواقتصادية،
and that paradigm is being challenged now too.
كما أن هذا النموذج أصبح أيضاموضوعا للتساؤل اليوم.
A lot of change.
الكثير من التغيير.
And the good news is, nine years later,
والخبر السار، أنه بعد 9 سنوات،
you can see improvements in quality and equity.
يمكنكم مشاهدة التحسنالذي حصل بخصوص الجودة والإنصاف.
People have taken up the challenge, done something about it.
لأن الناس قبلوا التحديوقاموا بشيء حيال ذلك الأمر.
Or take Korea, at the other end of the spectrum.
فلنأخذ كوريا مثلا،في أقصى الرسم البياني.
In the year 2000, Korea did already very well,
في سنة 2000،كانت كوريا قد حققت هذفها،
but the Koreans were concerned that only a small share
لكن الكوريين كانوا قلقين من أن جزء قليل فقط
of their students achieved the really high levels of excellence.
من طلابهم حققوا أعلى مراتب التفوق.
They took up the challenge,
قبلوا التحدي،
and Korea was able to double the proportion of students
كانت كوريا قادرة على مضاعفة نسبة الطلاب
achieving excellence in one decade in the field of reading.
الذين حققوا التفوق،خلال عقد من الزمان بمجال القراءة.
Well, if you only focus on your brightest students,
و أنتم تعلمون أنهُوَة الفوارق الاجتماعية ستتسع
you know what happens is disparities grow,
إن أنتم ركزتم اهتمامكم فقطعلى ألمع طلابكم،
and you can see this bubble moving slightly to the other direction,
ويمكنكم ملاحظة أن هذه الدائرة تتحرك ببطءفي الاتجاه المعاكس،
but still, an impressive improvement.
لكنه يبقى رغم ذلك تحسنا مدهشا.
A major overhaul of Poland's education
ساعد فحص وإصلاح شاملللنظام التعليمي البولندي
helped to dramatically reduce between variability among schools,
من التقليل بشكل كبيرمن التفاوت بين المدارس،
turn around many of the lowest-performing schools,
ومساعدة العديد من المدارسضعيفة الكفاءة،
and raise performance by over half a school year.
والرفع من الكفاءة تزيد عننصف سنة دراسية.
And you can see other countries as well.
ويمكنكم أن تلاحظوا أن بلدان أخرىهي في نفس الوضعية.
Portugal was able to consolidate its fragmented school system,
كانت البرتغال قادرة علىتقويت نظامها التعليمي المشتت،
raise quality and improve equity,
والرفع من الجودة وتحسن الإنصاف،
and so did Hungary.
ونفس الشيء قامت به هنغاريا.
So what you can actually see, there's been a lot of change.
ما تنظرون إليه في الواقع هوالتغيير الكبير الذي وقع.
And even those people who complain and say that
وحتى أولئك الأشخاص الذين انتقدوا وقالوا بأن
the relative standing of countries
تقييم البلدان ببرنامج مثل بيسا
on something like PISA is just an artifact of culture,
هو أمر نسبيوهو ليس سوى قطعة أثرية من الثقافة
of economic factors, of social issues,
والعوامل الاقتصادية والقضايا الاجتماعية
of homogeneity of societies, and so on,
وتجانس المجتمعات وغيرها،
these people must now concede that education improvement is possible.
يجب على هؤلاء الأشخاص الاعترافبأن تحسين النظام التعليمي ممكن.
You know, Poland hasn't changed its culture.
فبولندا لم تغير ثقافتها.
It didn't change its economy. It didn't change
لم تغير اقتصادها.
the compositions of its population.
لم تغير تركيبتها السكانية.
It didn't fire its teachers. It changed its education policies
لم تطرد مدرسيها. بل غيرت سياساتها
and practice. Very impressive.
وعاداتها التعليمية. هذا مذهل.
And all that raises, of course, the question: What can we learn
والسؤال الذي يطرح: ما الذي يمكن أن نتعلمه
from those countries in the green quadrant
من هذه البلدان الموجودةبالربع الأخضر من الرسم البياني
who have achieved high levels of equity,
والتي حققت مستويات عالية من الإنصاف
high levels of performance, and raised outcomes?
والكفاءة ورفعت من نتائجها؟
And, of course, the question is, can what works in one context
وبالطبع، السؤال هو،هل يمكن لتجربة نجحت في سياق معين
provide a model elsewhere?
أن تقدم نموذج يحتدى به للباقي؟
Of course, you can't copy and paste education systems wholesale,
فبالطبع لا يمكنناأن ننسخ الأنظمة التعليمية بسذاجة،
but these comparisons have identified a range of factors
لكن هذه المقارنات فيما بينهاتعطينا فكرة عن القواسم
that high-performing systems share.
المشتركة بين الأنظمة العالية الكفاءة.
Everybody agrees that education is important.
الكل يجمع على أهمية التعليم.
Everybody says that.
الكل يقول ذلك.
But the test of truth is, how do you weigh that priority
لكن الاختبار الحقيقي هوكيف سنوازن بين هذه الأولوية
against other priorities?
وباقي الأولويات؟
How do countries pay their teachers
كيف هي الأجور التي تدفعها الدول لمدرسيها
relative to other highly skilled workers?
بالمقارنة مع العاملين الأخرينمن ذوي المهارات العالية؟
Would you want your child to become a teacher
هل تودون أن يصبح ابنكم مدرسا
rather than a lawyer?
بدل أن يكون محام؟
How do the media talk about schools and teachers?
كيف يتحدث الإعلام عن المدارس والمدرسين؟
Those are the critical questions, and what we have learned
هذه هي الأسئلة المهمة، وما تعلمناه
from PISA is that, in high-performing education systems,
من برنامج پيسا هو،في الأنظمة التعليمية ذات الكفاءة العالية،
the leaders have convinced their citizens to make choices
قام قادة المجتمعبإقناع المواطنين باتخاذ اختيارات
that value education, their future,
جعلت من التعليم قيمة مهمة لمستقبلهم،
more than consumption today.
أكثر من الاستهلاك.
And you know what's interesting? You won't believe it,
وهل تعلمون ما المثير بالأمر؟لن تصدقوا ذلك!
but there are countries in which the most attractive place
هناك بعض البلدان حيث تعتبر المدرسة أكثر
to be is not the shopping center but the school.
تسلية من مركز التسوق.
Those things really exist.
هذه الأشياء موجودة حقا.
But placing a high value on education
لكن المراهنة على التعليم
is just part of the picture.
ليس سوى الوجه الأول من العملة.
The other part is the belief that all children
الوجه الثاني هو الإيمان بأن كل الأطفال
are capable of success.
قادرين على النجاح.
You have some countries where students
لديكم مثلا بعض البلدان التي تفصل
are segregated early in their ages.
بين الطلاب منذ مراحل مبكرة من العمر.
You know, students are divided up,
حيث يقسم الأطفال،
reflecting the belief that only some children
الشيء الذي يعكس الاعتقاد بأنالبعض فقط من الأطفال
can achieve world-class standards.
قادرين على بلوغ المعايير العالمية.
But usually that is linked to very strong social disparities.
لكن ذلك مرتبط في الواقعبالفوارق الاجتماعية القوية بالمجتمع.
If you go to Japan in Asia, or Finland in Europe,
إن أنتم ذهبتم إلىالياپان في آسيا أو فنلندا يأوروبا،
parents and teachers in those countries
ستجدون أن الأباء والمدرسين بهذين البلدين
expect every student to succeed,
يتوقعون أن كل طالب قادر على النجاح،
and you can see that actually mirrored in student behavior.
ويمكنكم في الواقعملاحظة أن تصرفاتهم تعكس ذلك الأمر.
When we asked students what counts
عندما سألنا الطلابما الذي يجعلكم
for success in mathematics,
تتفوقون بالرياضيات،
students in North America would typically tell us,
أجاب طلاب أمريكا الشمالية،
you know, it's all about talent.
كل شيء متعلق بالموهبة
If I'm not born as a genius in math, I'd better study something else.
إن لم أولد عبقريا في الرياضيات،فمن الأفضل لي أن أدرس شيئا أخر.
Nine out of 10 Japanese students say
بينما أجاب 9 من 10 طلاب ياپانيين
that it depends on my own investment, on my own effort,
بأن الأمر يتعلق بمدى تفانيومدى الجهد الذي أبذله
and that tells you a lot about the system that is around them.
وهذا يقدم لكم فكرة عن طبيعةالنظام الذي يعيشون به.
In the past, different students were taught in similar ways.
في الماضي،كان يتم تدريس طلاب مختلفين بنفس الطرق.
High performers on PISA embrace diversity
الكفاءات العاليةحسب برنامج پيسا تقبل بالتنوع
with differentiated pedagogical practices.
مع ممارسات تربوية متميزة.
They realize that
أدركوا بأن
ordinary students have extraordinary talents,
الطلاب العاديين يملكون مواهب استثنائيةـ
and they personalize learning opportunities.
فقاموا بتعديل فرص التعلم.
High-performing systems also share
وتتشاركالأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية أيضا في
clear and ambitious standards across the entire spectrum.
معاييرها الواضحة والطموحةعلى جميع الأصعدة.
Every student knows what matters.
كل طالب يعلم ما هي الأولويات.
Every student knows what's required to be successful.
كل طالب يعلم ما يتطلبه النجاح.
And nowhere does the quality of an education system
ولا يوجد نظام تعلو فيه جودة التعليم
exceed the quality of its teachers.
عن جودة مدرسيه.
High-performing systems are very careful
فالأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية دقيقة جدا
in how they recruit and select their teachers
في كيفية توظيفها وانتقاءها لمدرسيها
and how they train them.
وكذا طريقة تكوينها لهم.
They watch how they improve the performances of teachers
فهي تبحث عن طريقةتمكنها من تحسين كفاءات المدرسين
in difficulties who are struggling,
ضد الصعوبات التي يواجهونها.
and how they structure teacher pay.
وعن طريقة لهيكلة أجور المدرسين.
They provide an environment also in which teachers work together
كما توفر المناخ المناسبالذي يمكن المدرسين من العمل معا
to frame good practice.
لخلق ممارسات جيدة.
And they provide intelligent pathways for teachers to grow
وتوفر مسارات مهنية ذكية للمدرسين للتقدم
in their careers.
في حياتهم المهنية.
In bureaucratic school systems,
في الأنظمة المدرسية البيروقراطية،
teachers are often left alone in classrooms
غالبا ما يُتْرَكُ المدرسين بمفردهم بالأقسام
with a lot of prescription on what they should be teaching.
مع الكثير من التوجيهات حولما يجب تدريسه.
High-performing systems are very clear what good performance is.
تتمتع الأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية برؤية واضحةحول ماهية الكفاءة.
They set very ambitious standards, but then they enable
وتضع معايير طموحة لتمكن
their teachers to figure out,
مدرسيها من تحديد
what do I need to teach to my students today?
ما الذي يريدون تدريسه لطلابهم اليوم؟
The past was about delivered wisdom in education.
كان التعليم فيما مضى يهتم بتقديم الحكمة.
Now the challenge is to enable user-generated wisdom.
أصبح التحدي اليوم هو تمكين الفاعلينفي التربية من تقديم تلك الحكمة.
High performers have moved on from professional
لقد انتقلت الكفاءات العالية من النماذج المهنية
or from administrative forms of accountability and control --
أو الإدارية التقليدية في مجال المسائلة والرقابة --
sort of, how do you check whether people do what they're supposed to do in education --
التي هي عبارة عن طرق للتأكد من أنالكل يقوم بما هو مطلوب منه --
to professional forms of work organization.
إلى نماذج مهنية لتنظيم العمل.
They enable their teachers to make innovations in pedagogy.
إنها تمكن مدرسيها من الابتكار التربوي.
They provide them with the kind of development they need
وتوفر لهم وسائل التنمية التي هم بحاجة إليها
to develop stronger pedagogical practices.
لخلق ممارسات تربوية قوية.
The goal of the past was standardization and compliance.
كان الهدف فيما مضى توحيد المعايير والإذعان.
High-performing systems have made teachers
أعطت الأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية مدرسين
and school principals inventive.
ومديري مدارس مبدعين.
In the past, the policy focus was on outcomes,
في الماضي كان تركيز السياساتمنصب على النتائج
on provision.
وكيفية تحقيقها.
The high-performing systems have helped teachers
بينما ساعدتالأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية المدرسين
and school principals to look outwards to the next teacher,
ومديري المدارس للانتباه إلىما يقوم به المدرس
the next school around their lives.
وتقوم به المدرسة من حولهما.
And the most impressive outcomes of world-class systems
وتبقى أكثر النتائج إدهاشا للأنظمة ذات الكفاءة العالية
is that they achieve high performance across the entire system.
هي بلوغ النظام بأكمله الكفاءة العالية.
You've seen Finland doing so well on PISA,
رأيتم النتائج الجيدة لفنلندا حسب برنامج بيسا
but what makes Finland so impressive
لكن الشيء الذي يجعل فنلندا مدهشة للغاية
is that only five percent of the performance variation
هو أن 5 بالمائة فقط من التفاوت في الكفاءات
amongst students lies between schools.
بين الطلاب يعود للمدارس.
Every school succeeds.
كل المدارس ناجحة.
This is where success is systemic.
هنا حيث النجاح يأتي بشكل تلقائي.
And how do they do that?
فكيف يفعلون ذلك؟
They invest resources where they can make the most difference.
باستثمارهم لمصادرهمحيث يمكنهم أن يخلقوا الفارق.
They attract the strongest principals into the toughest schools,
يوظفون أقوى المديرينلأصعب المدارس
and the most talented teachers
وأمهر المدرسين
into the most challenging classroom.
لأكثر الأقسام تحديا.
Last but not least, those countries align policies
وأخيرا وليس آخرا،إن هذه البلدان تضع سياسات
across all areas of public policy.
تشمل كل مجالات السياسة العامة.
They make them coherent over sustained periods of time,
ويجعلونها متماسكةلفترات طويلة من الوقت،
and they ensure that what they do is consistently implemented.
ويتأكدون من أن برامجهم تطبق كما يجب.
Now, knowing what successful systems are doing
معرفة ما تقوم به الأنظمة الناجحة
doesn't yet tell us how to improve.
لا يخبرناعن كيف يمكننا التحسن.
That's also clear, and that's where some of the limits
وهو أيضا أمر واضحوكذا حيث تظهر بعض حدود
of international comparisons of PISA are.
برنامج پيسافيما يخص المقارنات الدولية.
That's where other forms of research need to kick in,
وفي هذه النقطة بالذاتعلى أشكال أخرى من البحث التدخل
and that's also why PISA doesn't venture into
وهو الأمر الذي يجعل برنامج بيسا لا يغامر
telling countries what they should be doing.
بإملاء الطريق التي على البلدان اتباعها.
But its strength lies in telling them
لكن قوته تكمن في قدرته على إخبارها
what everybody else has been doing.
عما يفعله الأخرون.
And the example of PISA shows that data
وبرنامج پيساهو دليل على أنه بإمكان المعطيات
can be more powerful than administrative control of financial subsidy
أن تكون أقوى من المراقبة الإداريةللإعانة المالية
through which we usually run education systems.
التي عادة ما نسير بهاالأنظمة التعليمية.
You know, some people argue that
يقول بعض الأشخاص بأن
changing educational administration
تغيير الإدارة التعليمية
is like moving graveyards.
هو كتحريك المقابر.
You just can't rely on the people out there to help you with this. (Laughter)
فلا يمكنك أن تنتظرأي مساعدة من أهلها. (ضحك)
But PISA has shown what's possible in education.
لكن برنامج پيساأبان عن الإمكانيات الموجودة بالتعليم.
It has helped countries to see that improvement is possible.
ساعد البلدان على الإدراك بأن التحسن ممكن.
It has taken away excuses from those who are complacent.
منع المتقاعسين من إيجاد الأعذار.
And it has helped countries to set meaningful targets
وساعد البلدان لتحدد أهداف رائعة
in terms of measurable goals achieved by the world's leaders.
من خلال أهداف قابلة للقياسحققها قادة العالم.
If we can help every child, every teacher, every school,
إن استطعنا جعل كل طفلوكل مدرس وكل مدرسة
every principal, every parent see what improvement is possible,
وكل مدير وكل ولي أمر يدرك بأن التحسن ممكن،
that only the sky is the limit to education improvement,
بأن لا حدود لإمكانيات التحسن بالتعليم،
we have laid the foundations
لقد أسسنا القواعد
for better policies and better lives.
من أجل سياسات أفضل وحياة أفضل.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)